<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at Oxford, before Sir. Will. Walker, Mayor of the said city, upon the 26th of July 1685 being the day of thanksgiving for the defeat of the rebels in Monmouth's rebellion / by Charles Allestree ...</title>
            <author>Allestree, Charles, 1653 or 4-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20829</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12294315</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12294315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 908:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at Oxford, before Sir. Will. Walker, Mayor of the said city, upon the 26th of July 1685 being the day of thanksgiving for the defeat of the rebels in Monmouth's rebellion / by Charles Allestree ...</title>
                  <author>Allestree, Charles, 1653 or 4-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Clements :</publisher>
                  <publisher>and sold by Joseph Hindmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Judges V, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Monmouth's Rebellion, 1685.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at OXFORD, BEFORE Sir Will. Walker, MAYOR of the ſaid CITY; Upon the 26th. of <hi>July</hi> 1685: Being the Day of THANKSGIVING, For the DEFEAT of the REBELS IN <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s <hi>REBELLION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Charles Alleſtree, <hi>A. M. and Student of</hi> Chriſt-Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Clements,</hi> and Sold by <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Ball</hi> in <hi>Cornhill</hi> over againſt the <hi>Exchange</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:58982:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58982:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Judges 5.31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the land had reſt forty years.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The whole verſe runs thus,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So let all thine enemies periſh, O LORD: but <hi>let</hi> them that love him, <hi>be</hi> as the ſun when he goeth forth in his might. And the land had reſt forty years.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is very eaſie for any Man, that conſiders the context of theſe words, and the ſtory upon which they are founded, to foretel the ſeries of my enſuing Diſcourſe, and to recollect in his mind both the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ariſes naturally from hence, and alſo to ſurmiſe the diſtinct ſort of proſecution, which at this time, upon this <hi>ſolemnity</hi> and <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,</hi> I intend to make: For whoever ſurveys the paſſages in this Hiſtory and compares them with the particulars of our late UNNATU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAL REBELLION, will find ſuch an Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Agreement, ſuch a ſutable Reſemblance
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58982:3"/>in every leading and preparatory circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that the ſame Trouble of repreſenting the Affairs of one WAR, will be a compleat draught of all the occurrences of the other; And as the parallel runs exact in moſt of the great Lines of both theſe <hi>Invaſions,</hi> ſo (I truſt, by the mercy of God) the event will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in all points, and prove ſo too, that our <hi>Land</hi> as well as <hi>Palaeſtine,</hi> upon this <hi>Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous</hi> and <hi>providential Defeat</hi> of our Enemies, may find the bleſſing annext here in the Text, of obtaining REST for FORTY YEARS.</p>
            <p>In this chapter <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> are making an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Song of Victory to the moſt High God, for the deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from the calamities of War, from the danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling under a <hi>forreign Yoke,</hi> and of being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by an <hi>inſulting, and devouring Enemy.</hi> Here we may obſerve <hi>Siſera,</hi> captain of the Hoſt of <hi>Jabin,</hi> King of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable enemy of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> bidding defiance to the Iſraelites Army, and invading the country with ſuch powerful Forces, as on the one ſide gave certain hopes of victory and ſucceſs to the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, and threatened no leſs, on the other, than an utter Ruin and Extirpation both of the <hi>People</hi> and their <hi>Government</hi> for ever. For the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58982:3"/>preparations (which <hi>Siſera</hi> made againſt this expedition) ſeem'd ſo formidably great, and conſiſted of ſuch vaſt Numbers of <hi>Experienc'd</hi> and <hi>Diſciplin'd</hi> Men, that He bore himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>Danger</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> and look'd for no more trouble in the Conqueſt of the <hi>Land,</hi> than the <hi>Fatigues</hi> of an <hi>Orderly March</hi> could put him to.</p>
            <p>Even the Mother of <hi>Siſera</hi> was ſo confident of her ſon's Triumph, that ſhe only waited for an expreſs of the News of it; She did not in the leaſt doubt of the event of Battle, or think that it could poſſibly be determin'd otherwiſe, than on her Sons ſide; She knew his ſtrength, the courage of his Souldiers, and the Conduct of their Leader, and therefore only wiſh'd for the <hi>Time</hi> of <hi>Action,</hi> and to hear of the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being poſſeſs'd with a ſtrong Belief, that <hi>Conqeſt</hi> muſt follow on courſe, and attend the <hi>Victorious Arms</hi> of her Son: In her Richeſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and beſt Attire, ſhe ſtaid at a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient diſtance from the <hi>Camp,</hi> expecting <hi>hour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to be brought to ſhare in the ſolemnity of the Triumph: <hi>She look'd out at the Window, and cry'd through the Latteſs, why is his chariot ſo long in coming? Why tarry the wheels of his chariots? Have they not ſped? Have they not divided the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58982:4"/>prey, to every man a Damſel or two? to</hi> Siſera <hi>a prey of divers colours, a prey of divers colours of Needlework, of divers colours of Needlework on both ſides, meet for the Necks of them that take the ſpoil?</hi> v. 28.30.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee the great thoughts, and the ſwelling expectations, they had conceiv'd of their Armies ſucceſs, and that they dream'd of nothing but <hi>Laurel</hi> and <hi>Conqueſt</hi> and ſo be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in the full ſpoils of the Iſraelites. All the Advantages that the proſpect of victory could lay before them, was the ſole entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their thoughts. The <hi>Slaughter</hi> of their <hi>Enemies,</hi> the <hi>Plunder</hi> of <hi>Cities,</hi> the <hi>Rape</hi> of <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and the <hi>Slavery</hi> of <hi>Captives</hi> was the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſcourſe &amp; expectation of theſe <hi>Invaders,</hi> and animated them with vigor and reſolution to maintain the Fight:</p>
            <p>And yet if we advert to the end, we ſhall find the diſcomfiture of theſe Forces, the Army ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd and defeated, and the <hi>General</hi> flying in a poor diſguiſe, in a habit beneath the dignity of a private Souldier, ſhifting for himſelf in <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Lanes,</hi> and <hi>ſecret Receſſes</hi> enduring the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of Hunger and Thirſt, depriv'd of ſleep and all the conveniences of Life, and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at laſt at a <hi>Lonely houſe</hi> for a cup of Water
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58982:4"/>to cool his <hi>Natural Thirſt,</hi> and to refreſh his Spirits with a draught of moiſture and ſleep. To that diſtreſs was this <hi>Mighty General</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, that He who, ſome hours before, had all the ſtores and proviſions of the Country at his command, and the <hi>richeſt pavilion</hi> in the Camp to reſt in, with his <hi>Troops</hi> and <hi>Guards</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him for his Protection, look'd now upon the offer of a little Milk, upon the Accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>private lodging,</hi> and the promiſe of a Woman's attendance, to be not only the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt kindneſs and relief to him in his diſtreſs, but alſo the beſt ſecurity to his Perſon, as he lay down to take his Natural reſt and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And yet as miſerable and as deplorable as his condition really was, it could not move any pity, or procure any commiſeration to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; The remembrance of his preceding cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties, and the ſenſe of the miſeries He intended to have acted upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> extinguiſh'd compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and left no room for the common effects of Humanity, ſo that the invitation of <hi>Jael,</hi> who diverted him from the <hi>Road,</hi> into her <hi>Houſe,</hi> prov'd a ſnare to him; She fully reſolv'd upon his <hi>Ruin</hi> and <hi>execution,</hi> and by one Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſtroke to revenge the diſturbance he had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58982:5"/>brought upon the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> neither the ſoftneſs of her Sex, nor the tenderneſs of her Nature could reſtrain her hands from act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Holy violence,</hi> or from aſſaulting the Perſon with Death, that deſign'd her Countries ſlavery; ſhe knew, that all <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Invaders</hi> have loſt their natural Right, and forfeited the protection of thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> which they come to ſubvert and deſtroy; She knew, that in <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary caſes,</hi> every Perſon, of what ever ſex, is oblig'd to turn both <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Executioner</hi> too, of their enemies, and that nature inveſts Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind with as much Authority over the lives of <hi>Rebels</hi> and Invaders, as over Wolves and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and other Beaſts of Prey; and that we ought to embrace the firſt occaſion to hunt and purſue 'em to Death; becauſe in theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, every delay of Juſtice, or Dilatory ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a legal Proceſs, may be dangerous, and expoſe the Government to a ſecond <hi>ſhock,</hi> For the flight or eſcape of an Arch-Traytor (which cannot by any method of reſtraint ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually be prevented as by Death) may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to proſecute his pretences again, and animate him with more Vigor to attempt a ſecond Tryal, and to revenge the diſgrace of his former miſcarriage;</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58982:5"/>
            <p>Guided therefore by this principle, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by an Impulſe from Heaven, <hi>She took a hammer, She put her hand to the nail, and her right hand to the workmans hammer: And with the hammer ſhe ſmote</hi> Siſera, <hi>ſhe ſmote off his head, when ſhe had pierc'd and ſtricken thro' his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. At her feet he bowed, he fell, he lay down: at her feet he bowed, he fell, where he bowed, there he fell down dead.</hi> v. 26.27.</p>
            <p>Thus was the end of <hi>Siſera;</hi> the calamity he intended to bring upon others, was executed upon himſelf, and return'd upon his own head; He died Ignominiouſly, and periſh'd by the weak hand and inſtrument of a Woman, and (as it ever happens in all Routs and Diſorders) left his Souldiers ſcatter'd and divided in ſuch ſmall parties in the Country, that they became an eaſie prey to their Adverſaries, and were ſlaughter'd without making any conſiderable reſiſtance or defence.</p>
            <p>When this Heroick exploit was wrought, and Vengeance fully taken upon <hi>Siſera, Jael</hi> ſtood openly at the door; and was prepar'd both to obſerve the <hi>Flight</hi> and <hi>purſuit</hi> of the enemy, and alſo to receive the <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> and <hi>Congratulations</hi> of the Iſraelites for her ſervice: She ſaw the <hi>Troops</hi> and the <hi>Chariots</hi> flying, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58982:6"/>promiſcuous <hi>Havock</hi> and <hi>ſlaughter</hi> that was made of the enemy; And tho' this indiſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating way of deſtruction might tend in ſome meaſure to the eſtabliſhment of peace again, and be a <hi>Political means</hi> to reſtore the happineſs of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet ſtill ſhe knew, that the Glory of puting an end to all <hi>Future Fears,</hi> was her work alone, and ſolely to be aſcrib'd to her <hi>Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>proweſs.</hi> For what advantage can it be to a Nation, to deſtroy barely the <hi>common herd</hi> of Souldiers, whilſt the <hi>chief Captain</hi> is eſcap'd in ſafety, and remains <hi>alive,</hi> to take all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of renuing his pretences again, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the cauſes of War hereafter? The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of <hi>Publick peace</hi> conſiſts principally in the death of him, whoſe Authority began and commenc'd the <hi>Invaſion,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Popularity</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> prevail'd upon others to eſpouſe and abet his cauſe with the utmoſt hazard of their lives; Now this political ſafety was wrought by her and perfectly accompliſh'd in the deſtruction of <hi>Siſera;</hi> and yet to make the <hi>ſecurity</hi> more laſting, and to engage the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>providence</hi> over the Nation, for the future, She calls <hi>Barak,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Abinoam,</hi> to ſhare in the joy, and to return <hi>Thanks</hi> to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the <hi>deliverance.</hi> She ſhews him the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58982:6"/>Trunk and body of <hi>Siſera,</hi> and relates the <hi>Holy Arts</hi> ſhe us'd to abuſe his credulity, and bring him abſolutely under her own power; And when all the Hiſtory was finiſh'd, and a full contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation taken of <hi>God's miraculous providence</hi> in this Victory, <hi>Barak</hi> jointly with <hi>Deborah</hi> (who at that time judged <hi>Iſrael</hi>) makes a ſolemne Form of Thanksgiving and Addreſs to the Lord for his <hi>Mercies;</hi> And 'tis obſervable that this return of praiſes, this <hi>National acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> procur'd the Bleſſing, which is mention'd here in the Text, <hi>That the land had reſt forty years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the word REST, is underſtood a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom both from Forreign and Domeſtick ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. For tho' in this place it is occaſionally mention'd, as an Iſſue flowing from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of Forreign Forces, yet it muſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and take in the other ſenſe alſo. For if a reſpite from <hi>Civil War</hi> was not equally meant, as well as an univerſal peace abroad, what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage could it be to the Iſraelites to be freed from the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> and yet be up to the ears in Blood themſelves, and be cutting one anothers Throats at home: It would be the exchange of one miſery for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a more dreadful and afflicting nature;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58982:7"/>ſo that in ſhort by REST I underſtand an unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted enjoyment of peace.</p>
            <p n="1">I.—From theſe words I ſhall firſt treat of the happineſs, which peace in general brings to a Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">II.—Secondly, I ſhall repreſent the great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of enjoying peace for ſo conſiderable a Duration, as the ſpace and compaſs of FOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY YEARS amounts to.</p>
            <p n="3">III.—And laſtly, I ſhall diſcover by what means this Bleſſing of ſeeing <hi>Publick peace</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed upon us and convey'd down to poſterity, may beſt be attain'd; and that is by returning <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> to God for every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtance of his providence, and more particularly for every great deliverance which he has wrought for a Nation.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed upon theſe Heads, I ſhall crave leave to ſhew the concurrence of our REBELLION with this which I have deſcrib'd to you from my Text; and ſhall examine by the way the reaſons and pretences that gave Birth and Growth to it; and in this proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſhall tye my ſelf up to the method of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it in theſe ſeveral parts of <hi>Reſemblance,</hi> both in the formidableneſs of the <hi>Invaſion,</hi> the greatneſs of our enemies hopes, and their utter defeat at the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58982:7"/>
            <p>We are aſſembl'd here, in obedience to our SOVERAIGNE's command, and in purſuit of his <hi>pious inclinations</hi> to render our utmoſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Adoration</hi> to Heaven, for the <hi>ſignal deliverance</hi> which God has been pleas'd to vouchſafe this Nation, and for the <hi>mercy</hi> of reſcuing us from the miſeries of a <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Inteſtine war:</hi> A War, that in all appearance ſeem'd to have been contriv'd for the deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of all that is <hi>dear</hi> to us, and to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd us all in <hi>Rapine</hi> and <hi>Blood:</hi> A War, that ſhak'd not only the Foundations of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but what was coequal to Chriſtianity it ſelf) our MONARCHY too, and was rais'd by SONS of BELIAL to have extinguiſh'd this glory of our ISLE, this race of HAEREDITA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RY MONARCHS, and the light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel alſo: A War, that was undertaken upon ſuch <hi>colourable pleas,</hi> and carried ſuch viſible danger along with it, that not only the <hi>preſent Age</hi> but <hi>future Generations</hi> were likely to feel the Bloody effects of it, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nborn Children</hi> might hereafter have been made ſenſible of it's Rage, and have been ſubject to the diſmal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of it: A War of the greateſt Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Dread that ever Hiſtory could give an Inſtance of, or our own apprehenſions frame
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58982:8"/>an <hi>Idaea</hi> off; For ſo violent were our <hi>Inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> occaſion'd by the falſe ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly</hi> and <hi>Fanatical party,</hi> ſo much heighten'd and improv'd were our diſcontents by theſe Mens induſtry and care, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious were the fugitives abroad of our diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and of the good affection the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> bore to their cauſe, that they preſum'd on Victory, and did not on the leaſt queſtion that ſucceſs would crown their enterpriſe. Their expectations were rais'd to that <hi>pitch,</hi> that in all their debates they had not any apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of being defeated, but their diſcourſe was founded upon the ſuppoſition of the ruin of the <hi>Government,</hi> and ſo their thoughts were wholly employ'd in the contrivance and choice of a new <hi>Frame</hi> or Model to be erected in it's ſtead. For when the two GRAND REBELS had concerted their meaſures, and agreed upon the INVASION, they neither of 'em ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd, that in the ſeveral Kingdoms, where they reſolv'd to <hi>Land,</hi> they ſhould meet with ſuch oppoſition from the King's Forces, as ſhould be ſufficient to retard their <hi>progreſs,</hi> or make any compitent head againſt them; No, they ſwallow'd that point, and took it for an indiſputable propoſition, <hi>that the preſent Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58982:8"/>muſt expire and end.</hi> All their debates in Council reſted upon this complex Queſtion, <hi>whether Monarchy ſhould be totally aboliſh'd, and a new Commonwealth created upon it's Ruins?</hi> And tho' their divided Intereſts would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to come to a full reſolution in the matter, and they left the diſpute to be decided by a conference hereafter, or (what is more likely) by the Sword, yet their deportment evinces the great aſſurances and hopes, and the full perſwaſion, they had of ſucceſs. For tho' this ſubject was not adjuſted betwixt them, yet they center'd in this reſolution to attempt the <hi>Invaſion,</hi> and make a <hi>deſcent</hi> upon this <hi>Iſland,</hi> in ſeveral places at once, that ſo the <hi>King's Forces</hi> might be diſtracted, and their friends have an opportunity of coming with eaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and joyning one of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which would have been a difficult task to men in remote places, had there been but one ARMY in the <hi>Field</hi> to invite and receive them. And yet this cautionary method did not ſo much argue diſtruſt and fear as prudence; For they could not be ſo diveſted of common reaſon, as to think that a whole Nation would run mad together, and as well vacate their <hi>Oaths of Allegiance,</hi> as cancel all thoſe other obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58982:9"/>which the endearments of our SO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERAIGN's Reign have laid upon us; ſome ſhew of <hi>reſiſtance</hi> they could not chooſe but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, and think that the principles of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, which the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> teaches, would unavoidably detain her <hi>True ſons</hi> under ſtrict ſenſe of Duty and obedience to their Prince. However the numbers they dreaded of this ſort were infinitely overballanc'd by the proſpect of all the <hi>divided Sects</hi> and <hi>Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents</hi> flowing into their Army: So that, in much confidence, they undertook with all the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary powers, they could collect abroad, to haſten to Sea, and begin their Voiage not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but, upon their firſt appearance upon <hi>Engliſh-ground,</hi> and Publiſhing a <hi>Declaration</hi> of the Reaſons and Motives that induc'd them to COMBINE, Ten thouſands of <hi>unwary People</hi> would have been prevail'd upon to joyne in the ſame <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and aſſiſt them with their utmoſt <hi>might</hi> and <hi>endeavours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed there were two pretences ſtarted, which being adverted to, and ſuppos'd to be the real truth, would have prov'd of more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and advantage to the <hi>late TRAITOR's</hi> cauſe, than all the ſuccors he brought along with him. The firſt was the common pretext
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58982:9"/>of protecting Religion, which tho' it never did nor ever can advance a <hi>Rebellion;</hi> yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail'd of being made uſe of to this purpoſe in every <hi>Civil War</hi> that has been commenc'd in a <hi>Chriſtian ſociety.</hi> And the ſecond was, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of <hi>Title and Proximity of Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe two conſiderations are very great <hi>Incentives,</hi> and are apt in their own nature to engage Mankind upon very violent courſes for the preſervation of 'em: For what would not people that have a zeal for God's worſhip, and an honour for the <hi>Royal ſtock,</hi> be inclin'd to do, to ſecure the purity of <hi>Religion,</hi> and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Deſcent of the Crown</hi> in the <hi>Right Line?</hi> And yet (as I ſaid juſt now) Religion is the worſt thing in the World to countenance or ſupport Rebellion: All it's precepts being of a direct contrary tendency, and enjoyning us O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the <hi>Supream powers</hi> under no leſs penalty than eternal damnation. And Chriſt who refus'd to have his perſon defended by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, will not ſurely have his Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated by ſuch means.</p>
            <p>But however granting that Men might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take up Arms for the maintenance of the <hi>True Religion:</hi> yet, even upon this ſuppoſition, No man can be authoriz'd to raiſe <hi>Rebellion</hi> in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58982:10"/>theſe Kingdoms. For has our RELIGION been in the leaſt danger of being invaded or ſnatch'd from us? Do we not enjoy it, and are we not likely to have it continu'd in all it's <hi>eſſential purity,</hi> and <hi>primitive Holineſs</hi> to our poſterity for ever. Have we not the free uſe of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and all the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of God uncorrupted for the aſſiſtance of our Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for the <hi>enlivening of our Faith?</hi> And have we not the promiſe of our King for the continuance of theſe <hi>ſpiritual enjoyments</hi> to us? Of a KING, that never had the imputation and ſcandal of breaking his Word, or dealing <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerly</hi> in any Inſtance of his Life? This is ſo remarkable a Character, and ſo peculiar to his Majeſty, that even his Adverſaries had never impudence enough to aſſault him with this <hi>charge,</hi> or to deny him the honour of being always <hi>Juſt and true to his engagements.</hi> We cannot therefore have any colour to doubt of the continuation of our Religion, or ſuſpect the faithfulneſs of that DECLARATION, which of his <hi>meer Grace</hi> and <hi>voluntary motion,</hi> he was pleas'd upon his firſt coming to the CROWN to make to his <hi>Honourable Privy Council,</hi> and renewed again in the ſame Terms in a greater ſolemnity, before the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58982:10"/>aſſembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi> Can any thing be more irrational and abſurd, than to entertain an opinion, that He who in private, betwixt himſelf and ſome <hi>Humble petitioner,</hi> has ever prov'd punctual and obſervant of his Word, ſhould now at the laſt turn inconſtant to his ancient courſe, and violate his <hi>Faith</hi> to a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when the whole Kingdom would become witneſſes of his <hi>falſhood</hi> and upbraid him with <hi>praevarication?</hi> Such a diſhonourable carriage on our parts would not only be a diminution of that <hi>Reſpect,</hi> which this Nation has ever been us'd to return their <hi>Reſpective Monarchs,</hi> but it would be ſenceleſs &amp; ridiculous in it ſelf, and contradict the common rules of reaſon.</p>
            <p>And yet if Men will be hearkning to their own ſuggeſtions of fear, and ſtudy their own diſquiet ſo much, as to diſtruſt every promiſe, and conclude it <hi>vain and eluſory,</hi> becauſe it is poſſible it might have been given with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to <hi>deceive,</hi> yet there is one unerring ſort of Tryal, one way of exploring Truth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing our ſelves, and that is by a continu'd <hi>Series and Flux of</hi> TIME. For thoſe that will not at firſt give <hi>credit</hi> to a <hi>bare aſſeveration,</hi> muſt believe the reality of that <hi>Mans intention,</hi> that made it, when there is nothing done in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58982:11"/>
               <hi>Revolution of time,</hi> but what ſtrengthens and confirms it: Now we have had half a years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of our KING's government over us, have had leiſure enough to obſerve the Juſtice of his Reign, and find all events anſwerable to his firſt Aſſertion, that HE WOULD MAKE IT HIS ENDEAVOUR TO PRESERVE THIS GOVERNMENT BOTH IN CHURCH AND STATE, AS IT IS NOW BY LAW ES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLISH'D.</p>
            <p>For have not all the Vacancies, that belong to the diſpoſal of the CROWN been carefully fill'd and ſupply'd with Men of <hi>Great learning and Abilities</hi> to ſupport our Religion, of <hi>Great zeal and inclination</hi> towards it, and whoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt is <hi>inſeparably</hi> bound up in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it? And can there be any furer Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the KING's <hi>ſincerity,</hi> than his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to make choiſe of ſuch <hi>inſtruments</hi> to fill the vacant places in the Church, who are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way qualified to maintain the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> both in their Abilities, and willingneſs of mind, and alſo are prompted to it from the conſideration of their own <hi>Temporal Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> All arguments conſpire for a ſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the KING's reſolution to keep inviolabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his WORD, and there neither is nor can be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58982:11"/>any ſingle inſtance produc'd to weaken or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate the credit of it.</p>
            <p>So that granting we might fight for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if it was in danger of being loſt, yet no man upon this Plea, can be juſtify'd in his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon the preſent conſtitution and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and it is ſurely much better and more agreable to the precepts of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to ſit ſtill, and enjoy it with <hi>content and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi> than by engaging in Rebellion to loſe and deſtroy it. For that would certainly have been the Iſſue, and we could have had no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> at all, had God, in puniſhment to this Nation, ſuffer'd the <hi>late Rebellion</hi> to have been proſperous and ſucceſsful. For what Religion could HE have been ſuppos'd to have been zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for, who had ſo far debauch'd the <hi>natural light of his conſcience</hi> as to eſteem <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> to be no ſins? I grant that, in a <hi>ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Transport,</hi> men may ſometimes be hurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the commiſſion of ADULTERY, and yet, upon a <hi>ſerious and particular repentance,</hi> be reconcil'd to the <hi>Church,</hi> and prove very good Chriſtians again; But He, that in his cooler thoughts, at the laſt Hour, with all his ſenſes entire, and the full uſe of his judgment, ſhall undertake to palliate the ſin, or extenuate the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58982:12"/>guilt of it, is in a fair diſpoſition to receive any Religion, and may eaſily be brought to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the ALCORAN, and exchange <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity</hi> for <hi>Mahometiſm.</hi> So that if <hi>Religion</hi> can at any time bear mankind out in oppoſition to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> it would with much more reaſon have juſtified us againſt the late RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BEL's claim and pretenſions, even allowing his Title to have been juſt; But indeed our <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution</hi> can do no ſuch thing, it is as far from giving Indulgence to invade any Man's <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Property,</hi> as it is from excuſing any ſeditious practice againſt a Lawful Governour: tho' it muſt neceſſarily have oblig'd us to have reſiſted his Uſurpation upon another ſcore, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of the <hi>Inſufficiency of his Title,</hi> which comes next to be conſider'd.</p>
            <p>Now this is a ſubject which has been ſearch'd to the Bottome, and examin'd ABOVE with all the fairneſs of procedure imaginable, in a <hi>Venerable, Juſt</hi> and <hi>Auguſt</hi> conſiſtory of men: And as it has been rejected there upon a ſerious and Impartial enquiry, as <hi>Fabulous</hi> and without <hi>Ground,</hi> ſo no doubt but, upon a rational diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, it will appear ſo to every conſidering man. For Firſt I will take theſe <hi>Two prelimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> for granted; That every Father has a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58982:12"/>tenderneſs and affection for his <hi>Son,</hi> than his <hi>Brother;</hi> eſpecially if there be no diſobedience in his <hi>Child,</hi> nor any deformity in his Perſon to alienate his Love from Him; And Secondly, I ſhall ſuppoſe, that it tends more to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a Father to have his Kingdom deſcend directly down upon his Son, than to demiſe it to a Brother or to any <hi>Collateral branch</hi> of His family.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things being premis'd, it is very obvious to recollect that never <hi>Father</hi> lov'd a <hi>Son</hi> with greater paſſion and tenderneſs, than <hi>our late moſt excellent Soveraign</hi> did the <hi>Duke of Monmouth;</hi> and never any man had ſtronger Reaſons, or more forcible Inducements to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage his love; For the <hi>perſonal qualifications and addreſs</hi> of his Son, the <hi>filial Duty and reſpect</hi> he always us'd to return in his Younger years, were ſo many motives to extort the utmoſt Tribute, which nature in this kind, could pay; ſo that the KING grew laviſh and profuſe in his bounty, He heap'd honours upon him, and loaded him with riches, and not only advanc'd him as high as 'twas poſſible for a <hi>ſubject</hi> to be promoted, but (what was infinitely above all honours) gave him the firſt place in his affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion: And when his Kindneſs had fix'd him in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58982:13"/>that <hi>ſtation of Grandure,</hi> as to render him <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular</hi> and courted by a <hi>Faction,</hi> when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd by the inſtigation of his <hi>party</hi> to lay claim to the Crown, and aſſert his <hi>Legitimacy</hi> by the <hi>promiſcuous mouths of the</hi> Rabble, and caus'd it to be whiſper'd abroad, that there were not only <hi>witneſſes,</hi> but <hi>Records under hand and ſeal</hi> of his Mother's Marriage to the <hi>King:</hi> His Majeſty (out of a juſt regard to the ſacredneſs of Truth, and without diminiſhing his love to him) did not only declare upon the <hi>word and honour of a Prince</hi> that there never was any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of Marriage betwixt Him and the ſaid Duke's mother, but ſummon'd the <hi>pretended witneſſes</hi> before him in <hi>Council,</hi> to ſpeak their knowledge, and give in their evidence concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the matter inqueſtion; Now they all of 'em ſeverally diſclaim'd the knowledge of any ſuch thing, or the being conſcious of any <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> that could atteſt it, and only ſaid that their names were abus'd for the ſupport of a Lye, without their <hi>privity or conſent.</hi> And this tranſaction, and the <hi>King's</hi> poſitive Averment was enroll'd in all the Courts of Record in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with the hands and atteſtation of every member of Council at the bottom of it.</p>
            <p>Now this Affair was tranſacted at a ſeaſon,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58982:13"/>and in ſuch a Juncture, when the KING had been ſeveral years married to the <hi>Queen</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hopes of Iſſue by <hi>Her.</hi> So that if truth had been induſtriouſly conceal'd and ſtifled at firſt for the better facilitating the treaty of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and for the removing the impediments, that might obſtruct this <hi>Illuſtrious Princeſs</hi> her conſent to the Allyance, becauſe upon ſuch a diſcovery her children muſt have been poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon'd, and allow'd to have only a ſecondary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the CROWN, yet now it might have been own'd and publickly avow'd without any detriment or damage to her Intereſt; and yet notwithſtanding this favourable conjuncture, and the extraordinary kindneſs of the KING towards him, his <hi>Legitimacy</hi> is diſclaim'd, and abſolutely deny'd with the ſolemn proteſtations of his <hi>Father;</hi> which is an undeniable evidence, that theſe were the words of ſoberneſs and truth; deliver'd purpoſely by that ADMIRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE PRINCE to prevent the effuſion of blood, and the great ſlaughter of Men, which muſt unavoidably follow the belief of ſtarting of ſuch a title. Nay even MONMOUTH himſelf no more believ'd that he was the <hi>lawful ſon</hi> of the late KING, than any man of this Auditory, or I that am arguing for the truth againſt this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58982:14"/>For in his Letter to our preſent SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGN (which you may find atteſted by the hands of two Reverend Biſhops, and other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Men of ſuch approv'd integrity and ſincerity that they cannot be ſuppos'd to cheat the World with a Lye) he voluntarily declares, that his Father aſſur'd him, that He never was married or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd in marriage to his Mother.</p>
            <p>Now what clearer proof or demonſtration can be offer'd to invalidate the belief of this man's right to the Throne, than to have his <hi>Legitimacy</hi> diſown'd by himſelf, and proteſted againſt by his Father, at a time when he lov'd him above all wordly enjoyments, and could receive no poſſible advantage by concealing the ſecret, and keeping it from the knowledge of the World? And yet the matters are thus clear, and 'tis evident beyond diſpute, that RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGION cannot juſtifie REBELLION, neither had MONMOUTH any ſort of right to the <hi>Imperial</hi> CROWN of this <hi>Realm,</hi> yet we know what a dangerous and formidable Rebellion was lately rais'd in the Weſtern parts of this Kingdom upon no other ground, but the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of impoſing theſe two falſhoods upon the World. Some people even againſt demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58982:14"/>will have that which makes for their Intereſt, and ſuits beſt to their inclinations, paſs for truth; or at leaſt they will lay hold of it and embrace it as ſuch, becauſe it may contribute to promote their Revenge and Ambition, or advance ſome other ſecular concernment: So that when the <hi>miſguided Prince</hi> had ſuck'd in theſe falſe principles, and landed in the <hi>Weſt</hi> to make good his claim, his Abetters flock'd to him in ſo great ſhoals &amp; numbers, &amp; ſaluted him with ſuch chearfulneſs and acclamations of joy, that in a very little time he grew ſo ſtrong, that neither he nor any of his followers dreaded the event of War, or apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a defeat of ſo numerous a body of Men, of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable courage and Reſolution; They preſum'd at firſt on victory, and thought their own ſtrength ſufficient to conquer and overthrow the oppoſition of their enemies; and yet they had ſuch moral aſſurances of new ſupplies, and ſo great an expectation of their <hi>Forces</hi> being multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, and encreas'd with the <hi>additional ſuccours and Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries</hi> of Men, that would be induc'd to follow their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that they turn'd their thoughts to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of diſpenſing Rewards, and dividing the great Offices of ſtate amongſt themſelves. To this ſtupendious height was their confidence advanc'd! and in all probability it had not been a vain or an impracticable ſuppoſition, had not the KING in his wiſdom provided for the preſervation of his <hi>Throne and Perſon</hi> by ſecuring, under <hi>ſtrict guards and reſtraint,</hi> all thoſe <hi>diſaffected Citizens,</hi> whoſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and diſcontents render'd them juſtly ſuſpected and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the Government, and by this <hi>providential poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> cut off the ſupplies of mony, which was ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed through their hands, and tranſmitted for the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Rebels, and for the maintenance of the War. (And by the way I cannot but obſerve that all thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who in other places were thus confin'd and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58982:15"/>for a time, are infinitly oblig'd to his Majeſty's good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and care, for uſing this compendious method to ſecure them from the Temptation of running into Rebellion, ruining their Families, and damning their own Souls for ever.) When therefore the ſource that fed this REBEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LION was ſtopt, when the Nerves and ſinews of War were ſhrunk, and monies fell ſhort in the Camp, they then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, by one bold attempt, to attack the ROYAL AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MY, and by the advantage of a <hi>ſurpriſe</hi> to force their way into ſome other Country for Relief and Aſſiſtance: Now this contrivance was form'd with ſo much Art, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd with ſo much Dexterity, Prudence, and Conduct, that had not God interpos'd, and miraculouſly baffl'd them with his own mighty hand, more viſibly than by any <hi>Humane power or ſtrength,</hi> they had not only made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves maſters of the <hi>Field and Cannon,</hi> but had ravag'd the Country, ſeis'd the <hi>Richeſt ſpoiles and Treaſures</hi> of the Camp for their Booty, and all the Enſigns of Honour had been ſo many Trophys of their victory. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Providence of God diſappointed their deſignes; the Stars in their courſe fought againſt <hi>Siſera,</hi> and even as inconſiderable and as unintelligent creatures lent their Aid, and contributed to the overthrow of our Enemies; For their Horſe were not able to ſuſtain the Onſet, or bare the diſcharge of a <hi>Volley</hi> without confuſion and diſorder; but fled upon the firſt ſhock, leaving their <hi>Infantry</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to ſeveral varieties of death, which were juſtly inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them without Diſcrimination or Mercy.</p>
            <p>Even the GENERAL himſelf, upon this diſcomfiture conſulted his ſafety by Flight, and attempted his <hi>eſcape</hi> in ſuch an ignominious Habit, that he appear'd really in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew, to be of that Low Rank and Order of Men, to which the hainouſneſs of his crimes had degraded him, and the juſtice of the Laws condemn'd him to before. He
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58982:15"/>try'd Two days the extremity of Fortune, and was not only diveſted of Friends, but depriv'd even of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſuſtenance of Life, Sleep and Neceſſaries. He durſt not venture himſelf abroad into the hands of <hi>Ingenious men,</hi> being preſs'd down with the load of his own Guilt, and fortified againſt a ſurrender of himſelf by the greatneſs of the Reward, that his head was pris'd at; But choſe rather to abſcond himſelf in <hi>Thickets</hi> and <hi>Woods,</hi> and to relieve his hunger with <hi>Peaſcods and green Fruit,</hi> than to expoſe himſelf to the mercy of a People, whom he had juſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd to the higheſt degrees of <hi>Outrage</hi> and Violence; When he had languiſh'd in this condition, and fed upon <hi>Bare Nature</hi> ſo long, that he groan'd under more <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral weakneſſes and Agonies of mind</hi> than the purchaſe of a Kingdom could recompence, He was at laſt ſeis'd by the vigilance of the Soldiery, and conducted ſafe to the <hi>Royal preſence,</hi> being inſenſible of his Guilt and offering no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of excuſe for the <hi>Cruelty of his Invaſion:</hi> The <hi>ſentence and Doom</hi> he receiv'd here was proportionable to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his crimes; for tho' it was circumſtantiated with Mildneſs, in regard to the honour of his <hi>former Quality,</hi> yet death being the end and ſatisfaction of the Law, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man meaſuring the Ignominy of it by the crimes that produce it, and his Treaſons being of the deepeſt Dye, we may pronounce that he dyed with more Shame and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace than <hi>Siſera,</hi> being made a ſpectacle to the World, and falling by the Hands of a publick executioner at laſt; <hi>And ſo let all thine</hi> (AND THE KING's) <hi>enemies periſh, O LORD: but let them that love him be as the ſun, when he goeth forth in his might. And the land had reſt forty years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe words I propos'd firſt to treat of the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which PEACE in general brings to a Nation.</p>
            <p n="1">I.—Now I ſhall no further proſecute this ſubject, or handle it in any larger method, than as it is introductory
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58982:16"/>and leads me to the conſideration of my next Head; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo plain and evident in it ſelf that it needs no <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration or proof.</hi> Every man will allow, that PEACE has the ſame important influence over the <hi>Body politick,</hi> as <hi>Health &amp; vigor of Conſtitution</hi> has over the <hi>Natural one.</hi> Without it no enjoyment can be reliſh'd, no pleaſures taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no Innocent Friendſhip or converſation delighted in, but even thoſe things, which otherwiſe would prove the moſt grateful Accomodations to the palate, become nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous or Inſipid. And is not mankind exactly in the ſame caſe, for all manner of enjoyments, amidſt the Noiſe and Rumours of War? How are the <hi>Generous and Great Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> (that ſpend themſelves and their ſtock too in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the publick) ſunk at the News, and let fall their endeavours, ſince the next Victory may raviſh the Glory of their work from them, and render it either a <hi>prey to the Conquerors Avarice,</hi> or a <hi>Victim to his Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> How viſibly, in ſuch a juncture, is Generoſity and Charity check'd and diſcourag'd? ſince the next <hi>deciſive Battle</hi> may not only alienate the Revenue it ſelf, but poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly eraſe the name, and make the memory of the <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> to be loſt too: How deſerted and unimprov'd lye all the Arts of Trade and Husbandry? how viſibly muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality be advanc'd? and the concerns of Families neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected? becauſe it is evidently the ſame thing in effect to enjoy no ſtores or proviſions at all, as to ſee 'em either Plunder'd from 'em in the <hi>Barn,</hi> or trodden down in the Field before Maturity: the ſame thing for mankind to leave no eſtate behind 'em for their children, as to ſee it violently ſeis'd before their eyes, and taken poſſeſſion of by Rebels and Strangers: nay more, how dangerous and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected doe even our Friendſhips, in the time of <hi>civil War,</hi> become? For no man can have ſuch an aſſurance in another, but he may reaſonably fear that ſome Temptation may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58982:16"/>prevail upon him to betray and Sacrifice his Friend, and ſo the conſidence, he ſuppos'd in him, may turn his ſnare and Ruin; In ſhort, not only our <hi>Temporal enjoyments</hi> but even our <hi>Spiritual concernments, Religion</hi> ſuffers and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expires in the heat and fury of a <hi>civil War;</hi> But in the Affluence of peace, we may (like the Iſraelites in <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen</hi>) enjoy a <hi>chearful ſerenity,</hi> and participate of all the <hi>Deſirable bleſſings</hi> that God and Nature can furniſh us with, whilſt all the World around us is in Darkneſs and Confuſion. The <hi>Land</hi> proſpers and flowes with <hi>Milk and Hony, Commerce</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> are improv'd, the reputation of a Nation exalted, the Sacred perſon of our KING re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd at home, and ador'd abroad for his Grandure and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, the honour of God &amp; <hi>his Religion</hi> promoted, and the great buſineſs of Devotion carry'd quietly on without interruption or moleſtation; and in fine all the bleſſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, that tend either to render us happy here or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, lye before us. PEACE therefore being ſo great a Bleſſing in it's <hi>conſequences and effects,</hi> I ſhall, in the Second place, recount the happineſs of a Nation, that is poſſeſt of it for the ſpace and compaſs of FORTY YEARS.</p>
            <p n="2">II.—Forty Years is not only a very great period of our Time, but has, ever ſince the flouriſhing of the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> been eſteem'd the moſt conſiderable portion of Man's life, in any Climate of the World; It muſt needs therefore be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd a Bleſſing, deſerving our utmoſt thanks, to enjoy this long ſeries and ſucceſſion of Time, in a conſtant ſerenity of Peace without any moleſtation of War to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer or pall the enjoyment of it. For whoever duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the time of Infancy, and obſerves how little obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoſe tender years are to the impreſſions either of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate calamities or publick ſorrows,</hi> muſt abſtract from the Computation all <hi>Minors or children</hi> under the Age of diſcretion, and date the beginning of his account from the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58982:17"/>expiration of Sixteen years at the leaſt: (for before the completion of that time, no perſon can in a due meaſure contemplate his own ſufferings, or be truly ſenſible of the miſeries of State) and from thence meaſuring the compaſs of Forty years, the ſum reaches to the period of a Man's ordinary Age, or at leaſt it brings him to that height and degree of it, which by the conſtitutions of all Kingdoms upon earth, is diſpens'd from <hi>Military ſervice,</hi> and exempted from <hi>Attendance in War:</hi> So that, in this ſenſe, the beſtowing of PEACE for Forty years, is in effect the granting a leaſe of it for a Man's whole life.</p>
            <p>But ſince <hi>Number</hi> it ſelf is not <hi>Infinite,</hi> much leſs ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable a quantity of it, and Forty years of Peace muſt ſpeedily be run out and ſwallow'd up in War, let us conſider the great Advantages that this PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISE brought to the publike, or to a new Race of men under other circumſtances, that did not ſhare the full time of peace, nor knew the beginning of it's Reign, and let us examine the great reaſon, which they had, to value the happineſs of ſo many Halcyon days, as had elaps'd over the Nation before their Birth.</p>
            <p>Now we know that the Iſraelites were a ſort of people that wander'd in the Deſert, and for ſome time had no fixt or certain habitation to reſide in; And even the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> which they did poſſeſs at laſt, was of a very narrow compaſs and extent, eaſily travel'd through in a few days <hi>March,</hi> and as eaſily meaſur'd with the Number of a few <hi>Paces.</hi> They were ſurrounded on all ſides with enemies, and they that hated them were their Neighbours; They had no <hi>Garriſons</hi> or <hi>Frontier Towns</hi> either to defend their Boundaries, or enlarge their Borders: And as they did thus lye open to the encroachments of <hi>every Invader,</hi> ſo they never were freed from the <hi>Incurſions</hi> of their enemies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a particular Miracle and Providence of God; and 'tis
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58982:17"/>obſervable that they-loſt more men in their <hi>Engagements,</hi> and in diſputing their Spot of Ground, than any of the <hi>Four Monarchys</hi> of the World ever loſt at a time in a <hi>ſingle pitch'd Battle;</hi> and theſe <hi>Encounters</hi> came ſo frequent and ſo thick upon them, that it is deſervedly eſteem'd a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, that they were not diſpeopled and brought to <hi>exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Is it not therefore, judging by all <hi>Humane meaſures,</hi> a vaſt happineſs to a <hi>Nation in theſe circumſtances,</hi> to be freed from the <hi>Terrors</hi> and <hi>deſtruction of War,</hi> and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy peace and plenty for ſo conſiderable a ſeaſon, as might enable 'em to repair their Loſſes with a new race and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Inhabitants, and give 'em time by <hi>Natural cauſes</hi> to encreaſe to that degree of ſtrength, as ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them to oppoſe and repel the force of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. So that certainly upon this conſideration, upon the account of the growth and Peopling the Land again, it was an ineſtimable Bleſſing to obtain the ſecurity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Reſt for Forty years.</p>
            <p>And is our condition ſo diſtinguiſhable in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar from the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that Reſt of the ſame duration will not be equally as great a kindneſs, and lay as univerſal an obligation upon us, as it did upon them? Have we not the like reaſon to rejoyce upon the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and aſſurance, being ſeated in a Climate ſo deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as invites not only the Viſits, but the Depredations of our Neighbours? Do's not the Richneſs of our Soil, the Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of our Land, and the Treaſures of the Inhabitants become a Temptation for the <hi>Inrodes</hi> of <hi>Invaders</hi> from <hi>abroad,</hi> or for the Aſſaults of Domeſtick enemies at home? Is not the happineſs of this <hi>Iſland</hi> ſuch an Invitation to Ambition, as Beauty is an <hi>allurement</hi> to a Rape? And have we not been ſo conſtantly harraſs'd, and almoſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled with War, that in all the Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> for the ſpace of Six hundred years and upwards, ever ſince
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58982:18"/>the CONQUEST, there has not been ſo long a <hi>Vacation,</hi> as to comprehend the ſpace of half this time, and give us a ſucceſſion of PEACE for Twenty years together? But either <hi>Inteſtine broils</hi> have diſturb'd our Reſt, or <hi>Forreign Invaſions</hi> call'd us to the vindication of our Honour, and to the Defence of our <hi>Country,</hi> by the <hi>Sword.</hi> Have we not reaſon therefore to lay hold of the promiſe of Reſt for Forty years, and to embrace it with all the joyfulneſs ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and diligently enquire after the Means of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſecuring it? which I told yee, in the laſt place, was to be accompliſh'd effectually by returning <hi>Praiſe and Thanksgiving</hi> to God, for every <hi>Signal Deliverance</hi> which he has been pleas'd to vouchſafe to a Nation.</p>
            <p n="3">III.—Now it is highly reaſonable upon this Account, becauſe in all victories God has not only a ſignal ſhare and part in the purchaſe; but ſome there are ſo miraculouſly atcheiv'd, and wonderfully wrought, that the whole ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is ſolely to be aſcrib'd to his immediate <hi>power and efficiency,</hi> and not to any <hi>humane policy and Conduct.</hi> And of this Nature was the Deliverance which we commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate this day, being viſibly effected by his <hi>Mighty hand and outſtretch'd Arm.</hi> We know that in all <hi>Engagements,</hi> the Glory of a Conqueſt (however purchas'd) is ever imputed to the Bravery of the <hi>General,</hi> that commanded and led the Souldiers on; And ſurely in a Chriſtian State we ought to advance the glory higher, and refer it ſolely to God, who in a peculiar manner is ſtil'd The LORD OF HOST: Now this <hi>ſtanding Appellation</hi> of Honour, which he has been pleas'd to give himſelf, was not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Temporary title, appropiated to the conſtitution of the Iſraelites, becauſe he <hi>perſonally</hi> led them to War, fought their Battles, and govern'd them by a THEOCRICY, but is adapted to the ſtate and condition of all the EM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PIRES upon earth, becauſe in every Country, he do's in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58982:18"/>an eminent manner preſide and Govern all Occurrences of War; And his providence, in no Inſtance of Humane Affairs is ſo viſible as in the Diſpoſal of the events of Battle. <hi>Not unto us therefore, not unto us but unto thy Name be all Honour and Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Beſt way to raiſe our <hi>Gratitude</hi> proportionable to the Deliverance, is to take a Proſpect and full view of the Complication of Miſeries, which the mercy of God has releas'd us from.</p>
            <p>Now what a Load and oppreſſion of Grief muſt there needs have been upon the Spirits of the preſent Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Men in the late REBELS ſucceſs? In that nothing that was <hi>Sacred,</hi> nothing that was <hi>Dear,</hi> nothing that was <hi>innocent,</hi> could have been ſuppos'd to have remain'd invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated in his proſperous and Triumphant Rebellion. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> it ſelf and the <hi>Royal Dignity</hi> muſt have been Sacrific'd, and troden under Foot: All the Religious parts of our Devotion would have been proſtituted to His, and his <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complices</hi> ſuperſtitious Avarice; The Revenue of the Church muſt have been alienated, and made an <hi>Oblation</hi> to his <hi>greedy Appetite and Sacrilegious Deſire.</hi> All the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Subject would have been expos'd, and lain wholy at the mercy of theſe <hi>Invaders.</hi> The Liberties of a Free-born People would have been Subject to his Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Will and pleaſure; and in ſhort the <hi>Lives and Fortunes</hi> of all Engliſh-men had been abſolutely dependent upon the Breath of his mouth, and, what is more, all theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries would have been entail'd upon <hi>Future Generations,</hi> and plagu'd Poſterity for a ſucceſſion of many Rowling years together.</p>
            <p>And ſhall not we in the loweſt poſture of Devotion and Humility, think our ſelves oblig'd to return our <hi>Thanks</hi> to Almighty God, that the <hi>Breath of our Noſtrils, the Anointed of the Lord is not taken in the Pit that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58982:19"/>for him, but is eſcap'd as a Bird from the ſnare of the Fowler?</hi> Shall not our Gratitude riſe in ſome Degree and Proportion to the ſenſe we conceive of the greatneſs of the Bleſſing? And ſhall not our Breaſts be fill'd with true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and expreſs it's motions in a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Return of <hi>Praiſe and Thankſgiving,</hi> for all the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that he has ſhew'd to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the wonders he has wrought for his Servant <hi>David?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let then the meditation and Reflexion upon theſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, which by a <hi>Signal providence</hi> we have eſcan'd excite in us a hearty Thankſgiving not only for this <hi>late Deliverance,</hi> but alſo for all the <hi>Publick Mercies</hi> which his Goodneſs has pour'd down upon this Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To him therefore, who is the Giver of all Victory, be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crib'd all Glory and Honour, from this time forth and for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
